Dwight James Baum Papers
Dwight James Baum Papers
circa 1922-1950
Baum, Dwight James, 1886-1939.
10 linear ft.
Papers of the American architect. Collection includes pencil drawings, miscellaneous published materials, and several hundred photographs (interior and exterior) of completed Baum architectural projects, mostly homes in Florida and New York State.
148836
Biographical History
Dwight James Baum (1886-1939) was an award-winning American architect and writer on architecture. Much of his work was done in Florida; he also designed several buildings for Syracuse University.
Born in Little Falls, New York, Baum graduated from Syracuse University in 1909 and almost immediately began a steady rise in reputation and respect in his chosen field. He specialized in country homes and institutional work; among other things he designed Syracuse Memorial Hospital and the Columbus Circle area in Syracuse, the Westside YMCA and Trade School in New York City, and the Hotel El Verona in Sarasota, Florida. One of his largest projects was the mapping out of a 50-year building and expansion plan for Syracuse University, as part of which he was the architect for Hendricks Chapel, the College of Medicine (now part of Upstate Medical University), and the Maxwell School of Citizenship. Baum also served as architect for Wells, Clarkson, Hartwick, and Middlebury Colleges, all in New York State.
Baum also played a significant part in the development of Florida in the 1920s, designing among other things dozens of individual homes, a newspaper plant and a country club; serving on the board of architects for the complete replanning of Clewiston; and devising a new town plan for Fort Pierce.
Baum wrote many articles, and served as architectural consultant to Good Housekeeping magazine. His plans were exhibited at venues in Paris, London, Berlin, and several South American cities. His abilities were recognized numerous times during his career. He won bronze medals (1931, 1932, 1933) and gold medals (1932) from Better Homes in America, a gold medal from the Architectural League of New York, and in 1934 was awarded an honorary doctorate of fine arts from Syracuse University. On that occasion, Chancellor Charles Flint praised him:
"...for that rare combination of business and executive ability, precise knowledge of structural problems, thoroughness in coordination of plan requirements to the purpose of the project, discriminating cognition and realization of preparation and detail in design, along with a high sense of beauty..."
Baum was member of the Beaux Arts Institute of Design, American Federation of Arts, Architectural League of New York, National Sculpture Society, American Institute of Architecture, and the University Club of New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The bulk of the Dwight James Baum Papers consists of Photographs. Styles include Italianate, Colonial, Dutch Colonial, Georgian, and English. A few Pencil drawings by Eggers and Baum, and some Miscellaneous material (an index of wooden frame houses, some published material, miscellaneous other items) complete the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
With a few exceptions, the collection is arranged alphabetically by building or project name.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of leading architects. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Baum, Dwight James, 1886-1939.; Architects -- United States.; Architecture -- United States.; Architecture, American.; Architecture, Domestic -- New York (State); Architecture, Domestic -- Florida.; Architecture -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Interior architecture.; Interior decoration.; Architectural photography.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority of papers, gift of Dwight James Baum, 1967.
William Kip residence drawings, gift of Alice Cahn, 2011.
Inventory
- Photographs
  - Allyn, S. C., 27 exterior and interior (Oversize 1)
    Style: Formal Georgian
    Location: Dayton, OH
    Photographer(s): Gottscho, Samuel
  - Adams, George Matthew, 1923; 21 exterior (Oversize 1)
    Style: [Italian]
    Location: Fieldston, NY
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace
  - Baily House [MISSING]
    Style: Dutch Colonial
    Location: Bronxville, NY
  - Barnum, Mrs. Jerome D., 3 exterior before alteration, alterations to Queen Anne house (Oversize 1)
    Style: Colonial
    Location: Syracuse, NY
    Photographer(s): Fenner, G.
  - Burns, Ed, 4 exterior (Oversize 1)
    Style: Italian
    Location: Florida
  - Barrett, Walter, 19 exterior and interior (Oversize 1)
    Location: Tampa, FL
  - Bates, Nicholas E., 27 exterior and interior (Oversize 1)
    Style: Spanish
  - Bates, Ralph, 12 exterior and interior (Oversize 1)
    Style: [?]
    Location: Englewood, NJ
  - Barnes, Richard P., 3 (Oversize 1)
  - Baum, Mr. and Mrs. Dwight James, 45 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
    Location: Riverdale-on-Hudson, NY
  - Baum, Dwight James (office), 9 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
    Style: English
    Photographer(s): Cox, Howard; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards
  - Baum, Faljetto, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
  - Bonnfield (Oversize 2)
    Style: Unknown
    Photographer(s): Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Bridgers, Henry Clark, 8 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
    Location: Tarboro, NC
  - Bulkley, Dr. L. Duncan, 15 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Gottscho, Samuel; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Buckner, Thomas A. Jr., 1 (Oversize 2)
  - Boardman, Francis, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Bierman, 1 (Oversize 2)
    Location: [?]
  - Beichl, A. J. (Oversize 2)
  - Campagna, Michael, 10 exterior and interior (Oversize 2)
  - Campagna, Armido, 7 exterior (Oversize 3)
  - Campagna, Anthony, 35 exterior and interior, AIA corresp. (Oversize 3)
    Location: Farmdale, NY
  - Chapman, Mrs. J. Wilbur, 5 exterior (Oversize 3)
  - Chicago Pavillion, 7 (Oversize 3)
    Location: Chicago, IL
    Photographer(s): Kaufmann and Fabry
  - Contessa Villa, 18 (Oversize 3)
    Location: Newport, RI
    Photographer(s): Child, Frank H. (Newport, RI); Gottscho, Samuel
  - Collins, Dr. Francis J., [1936]; 8 exterior, 2 floor plan (Oversize 3)
    Photographer(s): Gottscho, Samuel; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Cooper, Clayton Sedgwick, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 3)
    Style: [Colonial]
    Location: 246 E. 48th St.
  - Chase, Mrs. Benjamin, 12 exterior and interior (Oversize 3)
  - Cooper, Creighton (Oversize 3)
  - Crosley, Powel, 38 exterior and interior (Oversize 4)
    Location: Cincinnati
  - Dailey, Clarke G., 14 exterior and interior (Oversize 4)
  - Delafield, Edward C., 18 exterior and interior (Oversize 4)
  - Dancey, Charles E., 5 exterior (Oversize 4)
    Location: Lynnbrook
  - Deneger, Armine, 6 exterior (Oversize 4)
  - Dodge, Cleveland H., 8 exterior and interior (Oversize 4)
  - Drumlins Country Club, 6 before and after alterations - See SU Archives for more information (Oversize 4)
    Photographer(s): Gottscho, Samuel; Smith, Lindsley and Arnold Commercial Photo System
  - Elliot, A., 4 exterior (Oversize 4)
  - Emery, Archibald C., 13 exterior and interior (Oversize 4)
    Location: Montclair, NJ
    Photographer(s): Duryea, Drix; Gillies, John Wallace
  - Evans, Englehardt, 11 exterior and interior (Oversize 4)
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards; Smutny, R. V.; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Fein, Robert, 2 exterior (Oversize 5)
    Photographer(s): Smutny, R. V.
  - First Baptist Church, 1 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Flack, Robert L., 12 interior (Oversize 5)
    Location: Yonkers, NY
  - Furnald, Dr. Lynn Fulkerson, 10 exterior and interior (Oversize 5)
  - Fuerth, Gustave, 1 exterior (Oversize 5)
    Photographer(s): Hewitt, Mattie Edwards
  - Galban house, 7 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Gallager, 1 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Galley, Charles, 3 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Gibbes, William, 26 exterior and interior, House Restoration (Oversize 5)
    Location: Charleston, SC
  - Griffin, Mr. John W., 4 exterior and interior (Oversize 5)
  - Hamilton, J. J., 4 exterior (Oversize 8)
    Location: 4456 Waldo Avenue, Bronx, NY [identified by researcher who is current owner, 5/14/2018]
  - Hammerstein, Arthur - "Wildflower", 25 exterior and interior (Oversize 8)
    Location: Whitestone, LI, NY
    Photographer(s): David, John Adams; Gillies, John Wallace; Gottscho, Samuel; McKillup
  - Law, Robert - "Lawridge", mostly exterior photos (Oversize 8)
    Location: Portchester, NY
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Gottscho, Samuel; Weber, Paul J. (Boston); Wurts Bros., NYC
  - Law, Robert - "Lawridge", mostly interior photos (Oversize 13)
  - Hatch, William A., 6 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Hannig, William, 6 exterior and interior (Oversize 5)
    Location: New York, NY
  - Heindricks, 3 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Hilbonn, 1 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Hoffman, William P. and Edna, 39 exterior and interior (Oversize 6)
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Royal Atelier, NY; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Hughes, Charles E. Jr., 4 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
  - Humphrey, H. D., 1 exterior (Oversize 14)
    Location: Belle Rose, LI, NY
    Photographer(s): Collins, H. Shobbrook
  - Hutton, I. E., 3 exterior (Oversize 14)
    Location: Ridgewood, NJ
  - Iselin, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 5)
  - Jacobs, 8 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Kass, 1 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Kip, 3 interior (Oversize 5)
    See also Drawings: Kip residence
    Location: Riverdale, Bronx, NY
  - K-House, 1 exterior (Oversize 5)
  - Lawrence, Richard W., 7 interior (Oversize 16)
  - Leach, 2 exterior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Pelham
  - Lewis, J. R., 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Hartsdale, NY
  - Little, Gordon, 1934; 3 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Little Falls, NY
  - Lyeth, J. M. Richardson, 13 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
  - Lyons, Burton, 5 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Hemstead
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Gottscho, Samuel
  - Malady, Miss, 2 exterior (Oversize 7)
  - Mayer, 2 interior (Oversize 7)
    Photographer(s): Lee, Schuyler C.
  - McQuade, George T., 8 exterior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Freeport, LI, NY
  - McNitt, 3 exterior (Oversize 7)
  - Middlebury College Women's Dorm, 15 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Middlebury, VT
  - Mullaly, Charles C., 14 exterior (Oversize 7)
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Kunze, William A. (Yonkers, NY)
  - Morrow, George K., 6 exterior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Whitestone Landing, LI, NY
  - Murray, John F., 4 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
    Location: Old Westbury, LI, NY
  - Nimock, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 7)
  - Patton House, 11 exterior and interior (Oversize 9)
    Location: Milwaukee, WI
    Photographer(s): Brackett
  - Park Ave, 227, 2 exterior (Oversize 9)
  - Pauker, [1934]; 3 exterior (Oversize 9)
  - Perper, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 9)
  - Pichetto, Stephen, 5 exterior and interior (Oversize 9)
    Photographer(s): Duryea, Drix
  - Pross, 1 exterior (Oversize 9)
  - Quinn, John P., 2 exterior (Oversize 9)
  - Riley, Ben - Arrowhead Inn, 28 exterior and interior (Oversize 9)
    Photographer(s): Duryea, Drix; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Ringling, John - "Ca d'Zan", 49 exterior and interior (Oversize 10)
    Location: Sarasota, FL
  - Ritt, 2 exterior (Oversize 10)
    Photographer(s): Howard
  - Riverdale Club, 2 interior (Oversize 9)
  - Rockwood, Nash, 6 exterior (Oversize 9)
    Photographer(s): Duryea, Drix; Gillies, John Wallace; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards
  - Rogers, Hon. Ernest E., 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 9)
    Location: New London, CT
  - Rowland, Richard A., 20 exterior (Oversize 9)
    Location: Rye, NY
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards; Smutny, R. V.; Wurts Bros., NYC
  - Sarasota Courthouse, 27 exterior and interior (Oversize 6)
    Location: Sarasota Springs, FL
  - Sarasota Homes Apartments, 9 exterior (Oversize 6)
  - El Vernona Hotel, 14 exterior and interior (Oversize 10)
  - Recreation Group (Spa), 14 exterior (Oversize 10)
    Location: Saratoga Springs, NY
  - Schwab, C. Albert, 18 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
    Photographer(s): Collins, H. Shobbrook; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards
  - Schell, Edward P., 6 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Schwencke, O. L. Jr., 12 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
    Location: Bayshore, LI, NY
  - Shea, T., 6 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Schillinger (M. E. Shea), 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Senior, 3 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Shenandoah Country Club, 3 exterior (Oversize 11)
  - Simpson, Frank, 17 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Skillman, 3 exterior (Oversize 11)
  - Smith, Hurlbut, 1 exterior (Oversize 11)
  - Snyder, Hofner P., 1 exterior (Oversize 11)
  - Soldan, C. S., 5 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Smith, J. Allen, 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
    Location: Chappaqua, NY
  - Sporborg, W. L., 15 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Stocker, E. D., 8 exterior (Oversize 11)
    Location: Richfield Spings, NY
  - Stouffer Restaurant, 14 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
  - Sullivan, Frank A., 7 exterior and interior (Oversize 11)
    Location: Westbury, LI, NY
  - Stevenson, Malcom, 2 exterior (Oversize 11)
  - Syracuse Memorial Hospital, 28 exterior / 48 interior (Oversize 12)
  - Syracuse University College of Medicine (see University Archives for more information), 11 exterior and interior (Oversize 10)
  - Syracuse University Hendricks Chapel (see University Archives for more information), 16 exterior and interior (Oversize 13)
  - Syracuse University Maxwell School (see University Archives for more information), 9 exterior and interior (Oversize 13)
  - Taylor, F. H., 4 exterior (Oversize 12)
    Location: Park Hill-on-Hudson, NY
  - Taylor, H. L., 26 exterior and interior (Oversize 12)
  - Tekenian, B. O., 4 exterior and 2 interior (Oversize 12)
    Location: Maplewood, NJ
  - United States Post Office, 6 exterior and interior (Oversize 13)
    Location: Flushing, NY
  - von Glahn, John C., 4 exterior and interior (Oversize 13)
    Location: Brooklyn, NY
  - Wagner, 28 exterior and interior (Oversize 13)
    Style: French - Normandy
    Photographer(s): Gottscho, Samuel; Taylor, H.; Weber, Paul J. (Boston)
  - Wells College - Macmillan Hall, 18 exterior and interior (Oversize 6)
    Location: Aurora, NY
  - Wells College - Dean's Cottage, 6 exterior (Oversize 6)
  - Wilds, Percival, 6 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
    Photographer(s): Duryea, Drix; Gottscho, Samuel
  - Wilds, T. Robert, 7 exterior (Oversize 14)
  - Winchell, Benjamin L., 5 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
  - Winslow, Edward D., 3 exterior (Oversize 14)
  - Wheeler, A. E., 1 exterior (Oversize 14)
    Photographer(s): Tebbs-Knell, Inc. NYC
  - Williams, William R., 2 exterior (Oversize 14)
  - Wright, Wade (Oversize 14)
  - World's Fair - YMCA, 4 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
  - World's Fair - Home Furnishings Bldg, 10 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
  - Wychwood, 19 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
    Location: Westfield, NJ
  - Wyeth, George A., 19 exterior and interior (Oversize 14)
    Photographer(s): Collins, H. Shobbrook; Gottscho, Samuel
  - Wylds, Robert, 4 exterior (Oversize 14)
    Location: Garden City, LI, NY
  - West Side YMCA, 114 interior (Oversize 15)
  - West Side YMCA, 22 exterior (Oversize 15)
  - Zinc, William, 3 exterior (Oversize 15)
    Location: Summit, NJ
  - Zoller, 3 exterior (Oversize 15)
    Style: F
  - Unidentified, 21 exterior and interior (Oversize 12)
    Photographer(s): Gillies, John Wallace; Gottscho, Samuel; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards
- Pencil drawings
  - Hartwick College (Eggers), chapel, library, dormitory (Oversize 8)
  - House No. 9, Dunham Company (Baum), details of downspouts, column tops, etc. (Oversize 15)
  - Kip, William B. residence (Baum), 11 drawings (Map-case 108)
    See also Photographs: Kip
- Miscellaneous
  - Citadels of democracy, camps and plans for men and munitions, 1942 (Oversize 16)
  - Congress of International Geography (Oversize 16)
  - Index of wooden frame houses (Oversize 16)
  - Rea, Mrs. William residence, blueprints (Oversize 15)
  - Salisbury, D.E. (Oversize 14)